Guide to the National Education Association-Commissions records, 1918-1982 NEA1002.RG
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
National Education Association Records-Commissions
1918-1982
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
National Education Association of the United States
NEA1002.RG
160 Linear Feet
Biographical/Historical note
The National Education Association (NEA) is the largest professional organization and largest labor union in the United States, representing public school teachers and other support personnel, faculty and staffers at colleges and universities, retired educators, and college students preparing to become teachers. In 2010, the NEA had 3.2 million members and is located in Washington, D.C. The group holds a congressional charter under Title 36 of the United States Code granted in 1906.
The NEA describes itself as a professional employee organization. The mission of the National Education Association is "to advocate for education professionals and to unite our members and the nation to fulfill the promise of public education to prepare every student to succeed in a diverse and interdependent world."
The NEA is a volunteer-based organization that relies upon its members to perform much of the Association's work. The members are supported by staff at the local, state, and national levels with the stated goal of "building great public schools for every student."
In 1857, Thomas W. Valentine, president of the New York State Teachers Association, issued a nation-wide invitation to teachers to unite in Philadelphia behind a common voice for America's growing public school system. After the meeting, the National Teachers Association (NTA) was formed with a membership of about 100. Minority educators were allowed to join at the start, but women were not allowed to join until 1866.
In 1870, the NTA merged with the American Normal School Association, the National Association of School Superintendents, and the Central College Association renaming itself the National Education Association. For the first 100 years of its existence, the NEA was controlled by administrators, and worked to further the interests of the "education profession" as a whole.
In the 1960's, after the first passage of a collective bargaining law for public employees, the NEA adopted union activities in addition to its operations as a professional association.
The NEA merged with the American Teachers Association (ATA), formerly the National Association of Teachers in Colored Schools (NATCS) in 1966.
In 1998, a proposed merger with the American Federation of Teachers (AFT) failed when it was rejected by NEA's Representative Assembly. Several NEA state affiliates have merged with their AFT counterparts, effectively forming a single association.
Over the years, the NEA has been a leader in national education reform and improvement movements. It has worked to improve the education provided to American school children through lobbying and campaigning on the local and national level as well as by promoting strong teacher education programs and continuous professional assessment and development.
Scope and Contents
This collection documents the commissions of the NEA. The collection contains nine series reflecting the bodies and their records. The nine series are: the Commission on Coordination of Research Agencies, Commission on Professional Rights and Responsibilities, Educational Policies Commission, Joint Commission on the Emergency in Education, National Citizens Commission for Public Schools, National Commission for the Defense of Democracy, National Commission on Teacher Education and Professional Standards, NEA Centennial Commission, and Legislative Commission.
Arrangement note
The collection is organized into roughly alphabetical series based upon the NEA's organization. Records have been allocated largely to their offices of origin and reflect the work done within the offices, departments, divisions and units. Due to the immense size of the collection and the constraints placed upon the finding aid by the archival management system utilized by George Washington University, the collection was further divided up into parts.
Organized into 9 series: Commission on Coordination of Research Agencies; Commission on Professional Rights and Responsibilities; Educational Policies Commission; Joint Commission on the Emergency in Education; National Citizens Commission for Public Schools; National Commission for the Defense of Democracy; NEA Centennial Commission; National Commission on Teacher Education and Professional Standards; Legislative Commission.
Conditions Governing Access note
This collection is open for research. Some files are restricted. Those files flagged as restricted are subject to review by Special Collections staff before being made available for research. As researchers request materials, a review of the documents will take place. Staff will remove any documents with social security numbers, employee numbers or other sensitive identifying information. Any document found including this information is closed for 90 years from date of creation, or until verifiable proof of a person's death is given. After these documents are removed the folder will be available for research. In some cases, items may be photocopied and redacted. The redacted copy will then be placed in the publicly available folder. All other materials in a folder will be freely available for immediate use and will be marked as having been reviewed by Special Collections staff. After folders have been reviewed using these procedures and the confidential materials have been removed, the restriction shall be lifted.
Labor unions -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Teachers; Education -- United States -- History; Labor unions; Educational law and legislation; Professional Employees; Professional Associations; Teachers' assistants
- Commission on Coordination of Research Agencies, 1921-1922; Series 1; 0.25 Linear Feet
  Arrangement note
  Arranged alphabetically by title, and chronologically within the same title.
  Biographical/Historical note
  In 1921, a Commission on Coordination of Research Agencies was created. The commission was founded to collect data and information on schools. The Research Division and commission worked together in early 1922 and devised a plan which would bring about a better sense of cooperation between the educational research agencies in the country.
  As such the commission quickly disbanded and was enveloped into the Research Division.
  "Addresses and Proceedings of the National Education Association of the United States Annual Meeting, Volume 60" by the National Education Association of the United States, 1922.
  "The National Education Association and Educational Research", by J. Cayce Morrison, Review of Educational Research, 1956.
  Scope and Contents note
  Series contains materials created within the Commission on Coordination of Research Agencies. The files include only one folder of minutes from 1921-1922.
  - Minutes, 1921-1922; Series 1 (Box 844, Folder 1)
    Separated Materials note
    Included "List of Educational Subject Headings", by L. Belle Voegelein, 1928.
- Commission on Professional Rights and Responsibilities, 1922-1981; Series 2; 82.75 Linear Feet
  Conditions Governing Access note
  The Investigations files are subject to review by Special Collections staff before being made available for research. As researchers request materials, a review of the documents will take place. Staff will remove any documents with contact information or other sensitive identifying information. Any document found including this information is closed for 90 years from date of creation, or until verifiable proof of a person's death is given. After these documents are removed the folder will be available for research. In some cases, items may be photocopied and redacted. The redacted copy will then be placed in the publicly available folder. All other materials in a folder will be freely available for immediate use and will be marked as having been reviewed by Special Collections staff. After folders have been reviewed using these procedures and the confidential materials have been removed, the restriction shall be lifted.
  Series contains materials created within the Commission on Professional Rights and Responsibilities. The files include agenda books from meetings, conference information packets, investigation files, meeting minutes, reports and studies, and materials from the Workshop on Professional Rights and Responsibilities.
  The investigation files are the highlight of these records and include notes, transcripts and details of the commission's investigations. The files cover a multitude of issues such as racism, desegregation, nepotism, breaches of contracts, and mishandled elections amongst others. These investigation files contain the source material for a final report which is often included within the files, or in the reports and studies section.
  The Commission on Professional Rights and Responsibilities was formed in 1962 as a combination of the National Commission for the Defense of Democracy in Education and the Committee on Tenure and Academic Freedom.
  The Commission retained its focus on investigating the state of education throughout the U.S. including issues such as perceived Communist influences in the educational system, ethical dilemmas and charges including teachers, school systems and principals where help was requested in settling issues.
  - Agenda Books [file 1/2], September 28, 1961-September 30, 1961; Series 2 (Box 844, Folder 2)
  - Agenda Books [file 2/2], September 28, 1961-September 30, 1961; Series 2 (Box 844, Folder 3)
  - Agenda Books [file 1/2], February 22, 1962-February 24, 1962; Series 2 (Box 844, Folder 4)
  - Agenda Books [file 2/2], February 22, 1962-February 24, 1962; Series 2 (Box 844, Folder 5)
    Contains "It's Older than the Consititution", "Fair Dismissal Systems Procedures for a School System", and "State of the Nation in Regard to Criticisms of the Schools and Problems of Concern to Teachers" (January 1961).
  - Agenda Books, June 27, 1962-June 29, 1962; Series 2 (Box 844, Folder 5)
    Contains "Professional Priorities"; "PR&R Handbook" (2 copies); "CTA Journal" (April 1962); "Rights and Liabilities of Teacher Associations in the Imposition of Sanctions" and "How to Cope with Attacks from the Fanatic Fringe".
  - Agenda Books [file 1/2], October 11, 1962-October 14, 1962; Series 2 (Box 845, Folder 1)
  - Agenda Books [file 2/2], October 11, 1962-October 14, 1962; Series 2 (Box 845, Folder 2)
    Contains "NEA Commission on Professional Rights and Responsibilities", "Fair Dismissal Procedures for a School System", "Defense Bulletin" (September 1962), and "PR&R Handbook".
  - Agenda Books [file 1/2], June 25, 1963-June 30, 1963; Series 2 (Box 845, Folder 3)
  - Agenda Books [file 2/2], June 25, 1963-June 30, 1963; Series 2 (Box 845, Folder 4)
  - Agenda Books [file 1/2], February 21, 1963-February 23, 1963; Series 2 (Box 845, Folder 5)
  - Agenda Books [file 2/2], February 21, 1963-February 23, 1963; Series 2 (Box 846, Folder 1)
    Contains "Guidelines for Professional Negotiation".
  - Agenda Books [file 1/2], October 24, 1963-October 27, 1963; Series 2 (Box 846, Folder 2)
    Contains "Guidelines for Professional Sanctions", "Mr. Novak", and "PR&R Handbook".
  - Agenda Books [file 2/2], October 24, 1963-October 27, 1963; Series 2 (Box 846, Folder 3)
  - Agenda Books [file 1/2], February 27, 1964-March 1, 1964; Series 2 (Box 846, Folder 4)
  - Agenda Books [file 2/2], February 27, 1964-March 1, 1964; Series 2 (Box 846, Folder 5)
  - Agenda Books, June 20, 1964-June 23, 1964; Series 2 (Box 847, Folder 1)
  - Agenda Books [file 1/2], October 1, 1964-October 3, 1964; Series 2 (Box 847, Folder 2)
  - Agenda Books [file 2/2], October 1, 1964-October 3, 1964; Series 2 (Box 847, Folder 3)
    Contains "Summary Reports 1964".
  - Agenda Books [file 1/2], February 4, 1965-February 6, 1965; Series 2 (Box 847, Folder 4)
  - Agenda Books [file 2/2], February 4, 1965-February 6, 1965; Series 2 (Box 848, Folder 1)
  - Agenda Books [file 1/2], June 23, 1965-June 25, 1965; Series 2 (Box 848, Folder 2)
  - Agenda Books [file 2/2], June 23, 1965-June 25, 1965; Series 2 (Box 848, Folder 3)
  - Agenda Books, October 7, 1965-October 9, 1965; Series 2 (Box 848, Folder 4)
  - Agenda Books [file 1/2], February 3, 1966-February 5, 1966; Series 2 (Box 849, Folder 1)
  - Agenda Books [file 2/2], February 3, 1966-February 5, 1966; Series 2 (Box 849, Folder 2)
  - Agenda Books, June 18, 1966-June 20, 1966; Series 2 (Box 849, Folder 3)
  - Agenda Books [file 1/2], October 6, 1966-October 8, 1966; Series 2 (Box 849, Folder 4)
  - Agenda Books [file 2/2], October 6, 1966-October 8, 1966; Series 2 (Box 849, Folder 5)
  - Agenda Books, January 1967; Series 2 (Box 1519, Folder 1)
  - Agenda Books, February 2, 1967-February 4, 1967; Series 2 (Box 849, Folder 6)
  - Agenda Books [file 1/2], June 28, 1967-July 5, 1967; Series 2 (Box 850, Folder 1)
  - Agenda Books [file 2/2], June 28, 1967-July 5, 1967; Series 2 (Box 850, Folder 2)
    Contains "Las Voces Nuevas del Sudoeste", and "National NEA-PR&R Conference on Civil and Human Rights in Education".
  - Agenda Books [file 1/2], February 24, 1970-February 26, 1970; Series 2 (Box 850, Folder 3)
  - Agenda Books [file 2/2], February 24, 1970-February 26, 1970; Series 2 (Box 850, Folder 4)
  - Agenda Books, February 22, 1971-February 24, 1971; Series 2 (Box 850, Folder 5)
  - American Federation of Teachers Membership and Affliated Locals 1963-65, 1965; series 2 (Box 4203, Folder 1)
  - An Anchor to Windward: A Framework of State Certification to Accommodate Current Developments in Differentiating Staff Roles, April 1969; series 2 (Box 4312, Folder 1)
  - Bulletin on Critics of Education, 1952-1961; Series 2 (Box 850, Folder 6)
    Included "Communist-Socialist Propaganda in American Schools", by Verne P. Kaub, 1953; and "Sing a Song of Friendship", by Irving Caesar, 1946.
  - Bulletin on Critics of Education, 1962-1968; Series 2 (Box 851, Folder 1)
  - Case Examples: NEA DuShane Fund for Teacher Rights, March 1967; series 2 (Box 4290, Folder 12)
  - Central Issues Influencing School- Community Relations in Atlanta, Georgia, 1969 August; Series 2 (Box 4645, Folder 1)
  - Conference Information Packets, June 1965; Series 2 (Box 851, Folder 2)
    Contains "Report of an Investigation, Louisville, Kentucky"; "Third National Workshop on Professional Rights and Responsibilites"; "Professional Practices Regulations"; "NEA Department of Classroom Teachers, Reports Resolutions and Rules Committees"; and "Defense Bulletin" (April 1965).
  - Conference Information Packets, October 1965; Series 2 (Box 851, Folder 3)
    Contains "U.S. Court of Appeals, No. 21438"; "Charter, Bylaws, and Rules of the NEA" (July 1965); "The Assignment & Misassignment of American Teachers"; "Action Programs When there is a Local School Crisis"; "Guidelines for Professional Sanctions"; and "Professional Practices Regulations".
  - Conference Information Packets, February 3, 1966-February 5, 1966; Series 2 (Box 851, Folder 4)
    Contains "Free to Teach" (1966); "Report on the Platform and Resolutions of the NEA"; and "Fourth National Workshop on Professional Rights and Responsibilities".
  - Conference Information Packets, June 1966; Series 2 (Box 851, Folder 5)
    Contains "Free to Teach" (1966) and "Agreement Between the New Haven Board of Education and the New Haven Teachers' League".
  - Conference Information Packets, October 6, 1966-October 8, 1966; Series 2 (Box 851, Folder 6)
    Contains "The NEA Plans for Change"; "How come Everybody is joining NEA these Days?"; "Taking the Grief out of Grievances in Public School Systems"; and "Maine, the Pine Tree State" (4 copies).
  - Correspondence/Memoranda, 1966-1967; Series 2 (Box 1519, Folder 2)
  - Defense Bulletin Democracy's Defense Through Education, 1965-1968; series 2 (Box 4290, Folder 13)
  - Developing Personnel Policies, circa 1963; series 2 (Box 4290, Folder 14)
  - A Differentiated Staff: Putting Teaching Talent to Work, December 1967; series 2 (Box 4312, Folder 2)
  - The Essence of Teaching: A Basis for Differentiating Roles, June 1970 (Box 4312, Folder 3)
  - Et Tu, Educator, Differentiated Staffing? Rationale and Model for a Differentiated Teaching Staff, August 1969; series 2 (Box 4312, Folder 4)
  - Fair Dismissal Standards, February 1969; series 2 (Box 4290, Folder 15)
  - Financial Support of the Public Schools of South Dakota, August 1967; series 2 (Box 4290, Folder 16)
  - Freedom to Teach - Freedom to Learn, August 1964; series 2 (Box 4312, Folder 5)
  - Grievance Administration, circa 1971; series 17 (Box 4290, Folder 17)
  - Grievance Pamphlets, 1979-1981; Series 2 (Box 4060, Folder 3)
  - Guidelines for Professional Sanctions, March - November 1963; series 2 (Box 4290, Folder 18)
  - Investigation Reports Abridgments: grand Prairies, Texas; Kelso, Washington; State Education Agency of Utah; Twin Falls, Idaho; Oglesby, Illinois; Mars Hill, North Carolina, June 1962; series 2 (Box 4347, Folder 1)
  - Investigations-Alabama-Anniston # 165, March 1965-March 1966; Series 2 (Box 852, Folder 1)
  - Investigations-Alabama-Birmingham #164, May 1965-September 1965; Series 2 (Box 852, Folder 2)
  - Investigations-Alabama-Mobile, February 1970-May 1970; Series 2 (Box 852, Folder 3)
  - Investigations-Alabama-Selma #149, January 1965-April 1965; Series 2 (Box 852, Folder 4)
  - Investigations-Alabama-Wilcox County #220 [file 1/3], 1966-1971; Series 2 (Box 852, Folder 5)
  - Investigations-Alabama-Wilcox County #220 [file 2/3], 1966-1971; Series 2 (Box 852, Folder 6)
  - Investigations-Alabama-Wilcox County #220 [file 3/3], 1966-1971; Series 2 (Box 852, Folder 7)
  - Investigations-Alabama-Wilcox County-Aftermath, 1970-1971; Series 2 (Box 852, Folder 8)
  - Investigations-Alabama-Wilcox County-Background and Summary [file 1/2], September 1966; Series 2 (Box 852, Folder 9)
  - Investigations-Alabama-Wilcox County-Background and Summary [file 2/2], September 1966; Series 2 (Box 852, Folder 10)
  - Investigations-Alabama-Wilcox County-Desegregation Suit, 1966-1967; Series 2 (Box 1002, Folder 1)
  - Investigations-Alabama-Wilcox County-Investigation Reports [file 1/2], 1967; Series 2 (Box 1002, Folder 2)
  - Investigations-Alabama-Wilcox County-Investigation Reports [file 2/2], 1967; Series 2 (Box 1002, Folder 3)
  - Investigations-Alabama-Wilcox County-Notes, Meeting Transcripts, 1966; Series 2 (Box 853, Folder 1)
  - Investigations-Alabama-Wilcox County-Photos, 1969; Series 2 (Box 853, Folder 2)
    Contains 21 photos.
  - Investigations-Alabama-Wilcox County-Poverty, 1964-1967; Series 2 (Box 853, Folder 3)
  - Investigations-Alabama-Wilcox County-Press Clippings, 1965-1966; Series 2 (Box 1002, Folder 4)
  - Investigations-Alabama-Wilcox County-Press Clippings, 1965-1967; Series 2 (Box 853, Folder 4)
  - Investigations-Alabama-Wilcox County-School Data, 1967; Series 2 (Box 1002, Folder 5)
  - Investigations-Alabama-Wilcox County-School Finance and Taxation, 1961-1971; Series 2 (Box 853, Folder 5)
  - Investigations-Alabama-Wilcox County-Special Committee, 1966-1967; Series 2 (Box 853, Folder 6)
    Included "Educational Directory 1966-1967", by State of Alabama, Department of Education, October 1966.
  - Investigations-Alabama-Wilcox County-Special Committee Comments and Staff Reports, 1966-1967; Series 2 (Box 1002, Folder 6)
  - Investigations-Alabama-Wilcox County-Teachers' and Students' Charges and Related Documentation, 1965-1966; Series 2 (Box 1002, Folder 7)
  - Investigations-Approval Slips, circa 1967; Series 2 (Box 853, Folder 7)
  - Investigations-Alaska-Anchorage [file 1/2], 1959-1962; Series 2 (Box 853, Folder 8)
  - Investigations-Alaska-Anchorage [file 2/2], 1959-1962; Series 2 (Box 854, Folder 1)
  - Investigations-Alaska-Anchorage-Distribution of Report, June 1961-August 1961; Series 2 (Box 854, Folder 2)
  - Investigations-Alaska-Anchorage-On-Base Education Association #166, June 1965; Series 2 (Box 854, Folder 3)
  - Investigations-Arizona, August 1969-February 1970; Series 2 (Box 854, Folder 4)
  - Investigations-Arizona-Finance, 1967-1969; Series 2 (Box 854, Folder 5)
  - Investigations-Arizona-State of Arizona, Senate Bill #87, circa 1969; Series 2 (Box 854, Folder 6)
  - Investigations-Arizona-"The Study Request", circa 1969; Series 2 (Box 854, Folder 7)
  - Investigations-Arizona-"The Study to Develop an Instrument to Measure the Adequacy of Present and Future School District Organization in the State of Arizona", 1969; Series 2 (Box 854, Folder 8)
  - Investigations-Arizona-Voting Sheets, November 1969-December 1969; Series 2 (Box 854, Folder 9)
  - Investigations-Arizona #275, November 1967-January 1968; Series 2 (Box 854, Folder 10)
  - Investigations-Arizona #306-Correspondence, May 1969-December 1969; Series 2 (Box 854, Folder 11)
  - Investigations-Arizona #306-Data and Information [file 1/2], 1967-1969; Series 2 (Box 854, Folder 12)
  - Investigations-Arizona #306-Data and Information [file 2/2], 1967-1969; Series 2 (Box 855, Folder 1)
  - Investigations-Arizona #306-Newspaper Clippings, 1969; Series 2 (Box 855, Folder 2)
  - Investigations-Arizona #306-Preliminary, May 1969; Series 2 (Box 855, Folder 3)
  - Investigations-Arkansas-Conway, 1964; Series 2 (Box 1519, Folder 3)
  - Investigations-Arkansas-Conway #100, February 1964; Series 2 (Box 855, Folder 4)
  - Investigations-Arkansas-Conway #100-Aftermath, September 1964-May 1965; Series 2 (Box 855, Folder 5)
  - Investigations-Arkansas-Conway #100-April 2, 1964 Draft, April 1964; Series 2 (Box 855, Folder 6)
  - Investigations-Arkansas-Conway #100-April 8, 1964 Draft, April 1964; Series 2 (Box 855, Folder 7)
  - Investigations-Arkansas-Conway #100-April 24, 1964 Draft, April 1964; Series 2 (Box 855, Folder 8)
  - Investigations-Arkansas-Conway #100-Clippings, February 1963-May 1964; Series 2 (Box 855, Folder 9)
  - Investigations-Arkansas-Conway #100-Comments on Report, April 1964-July 1964; Series 2 (Box 856, Folder 1)
  - Investigations-Arkansas-Conway #100-Distribution, April 1964-May 1964; Series 2 (Box 856, Folder 2)
  - Investigations-Arkansas-Conway #100-Documentation, February 1964-April 1964; Series 2 (Box 856, Folder 3)
  - Investigations-Arkansas-Conway #100-Preliminary Inquiry, February 1964; Series 2 (Box 856, Folder 4)
  - Investigations-Arkansas-Conway #100-Press Releases, February 1964-May 1964; Series 2 (Box 856, Folder 5)
  - Investigations-Arkansas-Conway #100-Questionnaire, circa April 1964; Series 2 (Box 856, Folder 6)
  - Investigations-Arkansas-Conway #100-Special Committee, March 1964-May 1964; Series 2 (Box 856, Folder 7)
  - Investigations-Arkansas-Pulaski County-General [file 1/2], March 1969-November 1969; Series 2 (Box 856, Folder 8)
  - Investigations-Arkansas-Pulaski County-General [file 2/2], March 1969-November 1969; Series 2 (Box 856, Folder 9)
  - Investigations-Arkansas-Pulaski County-News Clippings, 1969; Series 2 (Box 857, Folder 1)
  - Investigations-Arkansas-Pulaski County-Preliminary Inquiry, Supplementary Request, Notice of Hearing, 1969; Series 2 (Box 857, Folder 2)
  - Investigations-Arkansas-Pulaski County-Recent Developments, 1969-1970; Series 2 (Box 857, Folder 3)
  - Investigations-Arkansas-Pulaski County-Report, March 3, 1969; Series 2 (Box 857, Folder 4)
  - Investigations-Arkansas-Pulaski County-Report (Final Type), circa 1969; Series 2 (Box 857, Folder 5)
  - Investigations-Arkansas-Pulaski County-School District Meeting Minutes [file 1/2], December 1967-February 1969; Series 2 (Box 857, Folder 6)
  - Investigations-Arkansas-Pulaski County-School District Meeting Minutes [file 2/2], December 1967-February 1969; Series 2 (Box 857, Folder 7)